<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The happiness of brethrens dwelling together in unity discoursed upon Psalm 133, vers. 1, on occasion of the late thanksgiving, Feb. 14, 1688/9 / by John Collinges.</title>
            <author>Collinges, John, 1623-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5318</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26035</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09322444</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09322444</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42746</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33963)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42746)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1306:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The happiness of brethrens dwelling together in unity discoursed upon Psalm 133, vers. 1, on occasion of the late thanksgiving, Feb. 14, 1688/9 / by John Collinges.</title>
                  <author>Collinges, John, 1623-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 33 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.S. for Edward Giles,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXXIII, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42746:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42746:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HAPPINESS OF BRETHRENS Dwelling together in UNITY.</p>
            <p>DISCOURSED Upon <hi>PSALM 133. Verſ.</hi> 1. On <hi>Occaſion</hi> of the late <hi>Thankſgiving,</hi> Feb. 14. 1688/9.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN COLLINGES,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Edward Giles</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Norwich,</hi> near the <hi>Market-Place.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:42746:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42746:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>FOr the Diviſions of <hi>Reuben</hi> are great thoughts <hi>[great ſearchings]</hi> of heart <hi>(ſaith the victorious Propheteſs,</hi> Jud. 5. 15, 16.) Reuben <hi>was one of the moſt Potent Tribes of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>you will find,</hi> Numb. 1. <hi>that upon their firſt Numbring, there belonged to it</hi> Forty ſix thouſand five hundred fighting Men: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Numbring,</hi> Num. 26. Forty three thouſand ſeven hundred, and thirty. <hi>They had their Portion on the other ſide of</hi> Jordan, <hi>and were by that River divided lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally from their Brethren; but that is not the</hi> Diviſion <hi>here lamented. In a cauſe where the whole was concerned againſt a Potent Enemy, they could not unite, but</hi> abode <hi>amongst the</hi> Sheepfolds to hear the bleatings of the Flocks. <hi>The cauſe of this</hi> Neutrality <hi>is not told us, but what ever it was, it could not be juſtified, and cauſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the more conſiderate amongst their Brethren,</hi> great thoughts, <hi>great</hi> ſearchings of heart, <hi>and not without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: It is a juſt amazement to any, that any Men for a little</hi> Secular Profit <hi>and</hi> Advantage <hi>to themſelves, ſhould diſunite from their Brethren in Councels, and Actions tending to the common preſervation of the whole Body of which they are Members. This hath been our caſe in</hi> England <hi>for more than an</hi> Hundred years, <hi>Men to keep up their particular</hi> Dominations, grandeur, <hi>and</hi> Secular
<pb facs="tcp:42746:3"/> Gain <hi>and</hi> Intereſt <hi>have kept up</hi> Diviſion <hi>to the apparent hazard of the whole, at leaſt</hi> twice, <hi>or</hi> thrice, <hi>and this deſerveth great thoughts, great ſearchings of heart. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called to perform my part in the late Publick Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, I knew not what better Subject to pitch upon, than the Commendation of</hi> Unity, <hi>with a</hi> Perſuaſive <hi>to it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I thought this alone was a</hi> Real Thankſgiving, <hi>as well as moſt of any thing ſubſervient to the good of the Nation. Every one calls for</hi> Unity, <hi>and reflects upon thoſe who are (in their fancies)</hi> the hinderers <hi>of it, but they ſeem not to underſtand</hi> the way of Peace. <hi>Would they have an</hi> Unity in the Doctrines of Religion? <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs, they grant this unpracticable; nor will they themſelves own the</hi> Articles <hi>of our</hi> Religion, <hi>further than as an</hi> Inſtrument of Peace, <hi>and with a</hi> Latitude <hi>for their</hi> own ſenſe of them. <hi>Would they have an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns and Councils for the Publick Good, <hi>and in</hi> the performance of mutual Offices of love one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? <hi>To this all good Men will ſay</hi> Amen. <hi>Only, ſay we, this is inconſiſtent with any</hi> Perſecution; <hi>for how do they ſhew their readineſs to do</hi> all Offices of love one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>who make it their buſineſs to ruine others, by</hi> Fines, Impriſonments, <hi>&amp;c. Or how can they joyn in Actions for Publick Good, of whom you require (as the terms of ſuch Conjunction) things that their Conſciences tell them they cannot do without Sin? and others Conſciences tell them are no way neceſſary for that end; but wholly fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign as to the thing for which they would have them unite? Would you have an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion to uphold the</hi> Proteſtant Religion? <hi>All honeſt Men are agreed for this. But, ſay they, (and truly too) you pluck up</hi> Proteſtant Religion <hi>by the</hi> root <hi>that day, that you deny to every Proteſtant, the</hi> Judgment of Diſcretion, <hi>which allows to every Man a liberty to</hi> Judge of his own Acts, <hi>whether they be ſuch</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:42746:3"/> 
               <hi>as he may</hi> lawfully do, <hi>or</hi> may not do. <hi>For if a Man may act contrary to the</hi> practical Judgment of his own Conſcience; <hi>in compliance with the</hi> Commands, <hi>or</hi> Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions <hi>of others, calling themſelves</hi> The Church: <hi>The</hi> Papiſts <hi>have got a great Point of us, and ſeeing they have greater Numbers, and that of Learned men, than are of and amongſt</hi> Proteſtants, <hi>they grant it ſafer to be</hi> Papiſts <hi>than</hi> Proteſtants. <hi>Well, but ſay ſome, We would have ſuch an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion that all may joyn together in</hi> Hearing, Receiving the Sacrament, <hi>&amp;c. All good Men will ſay,</hi> Amen <hi>to this too; Provided, that they will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low all thoſe who are true Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt (if there be any in the World except amongſt thoſe of their Perſuaſions) to</hi> Preach <hi>and</hi> Adminiſter the Sacraments: <hi>And</hi> Provided, <hi>There be nothing added to</hi> Preachings <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what God hath revealed in his Word, nor to Prayers and Adminiſtrations of Sacraments beyond what God hath directed in his Word, which is a</hi> ſufficient Rule <hi>for</hi> Worſhip <hi>as well as</hi> Doctrine, <hi>except as to the common Circumſtances of all humane acts. We hear Men ſay, Will you allow nothing then to Humane Laws and Legiſlators? Yes, very much;</hi> 1. A Power to judge what is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and expedient in all Civil things for the upholding and managing the Civil Government. 2. A Power to inforce the Laws of God in Religious things. 3. A Power there alſo to determine the neceſſary Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of thoſe actions, ſo far as they are Humane Acts. <hi>But by the granting of theſe things, ſo much of ſome</hi> mens craft is in danger to be ſet at nought; <hi>So much</hi> Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence <hi>(as ſome count it) in danger to be deſtroyed, that I deſpair ever to ſee ſuch an</hi> Unity. <hi>Nor do I underſtand how it is neceſſary in order to Brethrens</hi> dwelling toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Unity, <hi>more than it is neceſſary to the Civil <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of a</hi> Corporation, <hi>that all Men in it ſhould ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:42746:4"/> 
               <hi>the ſame Trade by the ſame Method, and in the ſame</hi> Circumſtances. <hi>If Men be united in their common</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, Deſigns, <hi>and</hi> Readineſs <hi>to ſerve the publick, for their common Good and Advantage, and a readineſs to</hi> ſerve one another in love, <hi>it is enough for our Civil, and Secular Happineſs: and if they be united in a</hi> common belief <hi>of all things</hi> neceſſary to be believed, <hi>and all things</hi> neceſſary to be done, in order to Salvation, <hi>it is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion enough in order to our Spiritual, and Eternal Happineſs. The neceſſity of any other <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion is a</hi> Chimaera <hi>fit only for ſuch who cry out for</hi> Unity <hi>upon terms, upon which it is almoſt impoſſible it ſhould be had, that is, they cry out for</hi> continued Diſcord, <hi>under the Notion of</hi> Unity, <hi>This,</hi> Reader, <hi>is that</hi> Union <hi>which the following Diſcourſe pleadeth for, and directeth what ſeemeth to me the beſt means to attain.</hi> Now the God of Peace, which brought again from the dead, our Lord Jeſus, that great Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd of the Sheep, through the Blood of the Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Covenant, make us perfect in every good work to do his Will, working in us, that which is well-pleaſing in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt. To whom be Glory for ever and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42746:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſalm 133. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.</bibl>
               <q>Behold, how good and how pleaſant it is, for Brethren to Dwell together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WE have not in the Title of the <hi>Pſalm</hi> ſo certain a conduct to determine the <hi>occaſion</hi> of the Penning of it, as we have in many other Pſalms. It tells us indeed it was a <hi>Pſalm of David,</hi> but upon what occaſion Compoſed, it ſaith not. It is not improbably gueſſed that the occaſion of the Penning, was the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of all the <hi>Tribes</hi> in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> their King, of which you read, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5. 3. After <note place="margin">2 Sam. 5. 3.</note> the Death of <hi>Saul, David</hi> reigned ſome years over <hi>Judah</hi> alone; but you read there, that after he had reigned <hi>ſeven Years and three Months</hi> in <hi>Hebron</hi> over <hi>Judah</hi> alone, all the <hi>Elders</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> came to <hi>him</hi> in <hi>Hebron,</hi>—and <hi>made a league with him,</hi> and <hi>anointed him King over Iſrael;</hi> and thus now the twelve Tribes were become <hi>Gens una,</hi> one Nation. <hi>David</hi> might (very probably) upon this occaſion Pen this Pſalm, commending to them the keeping of this <hi>Knot,</hi> which God's Providence had made. Thus it excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently ſuteth our preſent occaſion, we being at this Day, in ſuch an opportunity of <hi>uniting</hi> all that <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Reformed Religion,</hi> as poſſibly our Forefathers for more than an Hundred years (till within our memory) have wanted, whether God will yet pleaſe to hide from us the things which concern our Peace, time muſt ſhew. However I could not but take the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42746:5"/> advantage of it, to commend to you the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Brethren.</hi> The words I have read to you is the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> of the whole <hi>Pſalm,</hi> the Proof of it lyes in the laſt words, the other Verſes are made up of two Similitudes, illuſtrating the general <hi>Propoſition.</hi> The Propoſition of the Pſalm, is that which my deſign is to make the Subject of my Diſcourſe, which I ſhall prove only, by opening the laſt Clauſe—<hi>There God commands the Bleſſings.</hi> The other Paſſages of the <hi>Pſalm</hi> I ſhall no further concern my ſelf in, than they will naturally fall under the proof of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
            <p>Prop.<hi>It is a very good, and pleaſant thing for Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to dwell together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Notion of <hi>Brethren</hi> in Scripture is of as great a Latitude as that of <hi>Neighbour.</hi> It ſignifies thoſe that agree <hi>in uno aliquo tertio,</hi> in any third thing, whether it be <hi>Blood</hi> in a more general Notion, and thus all Men are Brethren each to other: or in a more reſtrained Notion, thus all of the ſame Family are <hi>Brethren;</hi> or in the <hi>ſame more immediate Parents,</hi> thus <hi>Eſau</hi> is called <hi>Jacob</hi>'s <hi>Brother;</hi> or in the <hi>ſame Nation,</hi> thus <hi>Paul</hi> calls the <hi>Jews</hi> his <hi>Brethren;</hi> or in the <hi>ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;</hi> or finally in the ſame <hi>Faith, or hope of calling</hi> (as the Apoſtle phraſeth it,) thus we are called to <hi>Love the Brethren.</hi> As to the particular ſenſe of it in this Text, it doubtleſs ſignifies thoſe that were <hi>Members of the ſame Nation,</hi> and United in the main things with reſpect to Religion.</p>
            <p>It may be a more valuable Queſtion, what <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> this is predicated of? The <hi>Heb.</hi> ſaith no more than in <hi>One.</hi> I find ſome would have it only to reſpect <hi>Place.</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42746:5"/> But beſides that, this was ſufficiently expreſt before, by the words <hi>dwell together.</hi> Nor doth this always ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear Productive of any Happineſs, or Pleaſantneſs. And if it did it would ſpeak the Pſalmiſt only here commending the Happineſs of thoſe who live in Towns, and Cities, contiguous one to another, above theirs, who live in the Country, or places where Mens Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are at greater diſtances; which is too mean a Notion to ſuit <hi>David</hi>'s deſign in this Text. We muſt therefore find out ſome other Unity here intended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> refers certainly to the <hi>Mind,</hi> and ſo there is a double <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity:</hi> The one referring to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> the other to the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Affections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unity ſo far as reſpecteth the underſtanding, is a <hi>Oneneſs</hi> in <hi>Apprehenſion</hi> and <hi>Judgment,</hi> which is <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent</hi> to it, for every Man muſt judge of the <hi>truth</hi> or <hi>falſhood,</hi> the goodneſs or badneſs of a Notion as he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends it. Now this is an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> which is not to be expected, we may as ſoon look to ſee an <hi>Oneneſs,</hi> in the <hi>likeneſs</hi> of all mens faces, their features and complexions, as in their apprehenſions, there muſt, and will be while the World laſts, different abilities in Men to diſcourſe Concluſions from Principles, as differences alſo in their Educations, and improvements of their Reaſons; from whence Men and Womens apprehenſions and judgments are formed. I doubt whether any ſuch thing may be pray'd for: for what were it but to pray God to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make the World, and to Caſt all mens Souls in the ſame Mould? or to work ſome ſuch miraculous change up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all; for neither of which I know of any Warrant. Beſides, ſuppoſing that the <hi>will muſt follow the dictate of the underſtanding,</hi> it would (with a witneſs too) deſtroy all liberty of the will, which ſome ſo contend for. Nor do I know whether this would produce any ſuch Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Indeed there is an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> that is deſirable;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42746:6"/> But that is ſecured by Mens rightly apprehending and <hi>Judging,</hi> in all things neceſſary to be believed and done in order to <hi>Salvation.</hi> But when ſhall we be agreed what thoſe are? I do not think that Unity is at all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in my Text. It muſt therefore be <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Will and Affections.</hi> And this either reſpects, 1. <hi>Deſigns and Councels.</hi> Or, 2. <hi>Offices of Love and Charity.</hi> 1. Tho' Men as to particular Notions may have different apprehenſions, and Judgments, yet they may have a <hi>oneneſs of Will</hi> and <hi>Deſign</hi> for the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome general good, let it be, <hi>the Glory of God,</hi> or the <hi>common good</hi> of <hi>the City</hi> or Community, in which we are involved. Now there are two things which give a liberty for this, under different Apprehenſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That a Man may practice, according to, or contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to many particular Notions, and yet glorifie God, if he lives up to the Dictate of his own Conſcience.</hi> This the Apoſtle abundantly determines, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. in the caſe of the <hi>Jewiſh Holy days and Meats.</hi> v. 6. <hi>He that regardeth a day regardeth it to the Lord;</hi> [that is to the Glory of God] <hi>and be that regardeth it not, to the Lord he doth not regard it. He that eateth, eateth to the Lord, and giveth God thanks: and he that eateth not, to the Lord he eateth not, and giveth God thanks.</hi> Thus it is in all things which God's Word hath left indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. God's Glory is neither concerned, in the doing, or not doing of them. Thoſe who think a Superiour's command afters the caſe, ſhould do well to conſider whether Saint <hi>Paul</hi> might at that time, have by his command made it neceſſary for any Jew turn'd to the Chriſtian Faith, to have kept the <hi>Jewiſh days,</hi> or to have <hi>for born the Meats</hi> there ſpoken of. What ſhall he ſay (ſaith <hi>Solomon) that comes after the King, even the ſame thing that hath been ſaid before?</hi> What ſhall God's Vicegerent ſay, or do, who in any thing cometh after
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42746:6"/> the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings;</hi> ſurely nothing but what hath been ſaid before him (in the things of God) <hi>commanding things neceſſary,</hi> and <hi>leaving things indifferent,</hi> as God hath left them. I never read but that the good Kings of God's ancient People, and <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles did ſo, not pretending to a Wiſdom paramount to that of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond thing is, <hi>That in all Civil things, a man in Obedience to the higher Powers, may, and ought to act contrary to his own Opinion and Judgment.</hi> The Reaſons for this are obvious.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>He tranſgreſſeth no Law of God in doing it.</hi> 2. Nay, <hi>he obeyeth the Law of God in it.</hi> Tho' the Law of God in <hi>Religious Matters</hi> obligeth every Man to follow the dictate of his own Conſcience, judging a thing lawful or unlawful; (and in things indifferent judging a thing more, or leſs expedient; becauſe in all ſuch things next after God, a Man's practical Conſcience is the Supream Judge as to his actions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Yet in <hi>Civil Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> the <hi>Higher Powers of States and Kingdoms</hi> are plainly <hi>Judges</hi> betwixt God and our practical Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; God hath clothed them with Power to make Laws, and determine of things <hi>neceſſary,</hi> or not <hi>neceſſary, expedient,</hi> or not <hi>expedient</hi> for the better managery of their particular Governments. That text, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. is to be reſtrained to ſuch things, it is reſtrained, <hi>v.</hi> 8. to <hi>matters betwixt blood and blood, plea and plea, ſtroke and ſtroke, matters of Judgment,</hi> &amp;c. and moſt imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently urged further. Now ſuppoſe a Thouſand Men, half of which judge ſuch a Law for a Tax or a Cuſtom, neceſſary or expedient; the other half judge it unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and inexpedient, they are none of them <hi>Judges of the publick Good</hi> of a Nation or City; but the chief Magiſtrate, is by God left Judge in the caſe. What ſhould hinder but that all theſe Men ſhould Unite in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42746:7"/> their Deſigns, Councels, and Practice for the Publick Good. And this is the unqueſtionable Duty of them all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond Union referring to the <hi>Will,</hi> I call'd the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Love and Charity.</hi> That is, <hi>when all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in any community are agreed in what they may to do all Offices of Love each to other.</hi> I ſee nothing can hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this, but Mens <hi>paſſions,</hi> and <hi>luſts,</hi> Pride, Envy, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, Hatred of one another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I hear ſome pleading for another <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> which they call <hi>an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> and expound by <hi>a reſorting to the ſame Church to offer up united Prayers and Praiſes, and together to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament,</hi> and telling us, <hi>That an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in Love, Charity, and mutual forbearance, is very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, when Men divide Communion,</hi> and why I pray? <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Mens not joining in Communion one with other, is in effect a declaring them with whom we do not join, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and Publicans.</hi> Now I muſt confeſs this is a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine I cannot underſtand.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Is there then any Church to be found ſo large as to hold all Chriſtians who are obliged to live together in Unity? But it will be ſaid, tho' they meet in ſeveral places, yet they are one in their worſhip?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Very well; but what is meant by <hi>Worſhip?</hi> only the <hi>ſpecifical,</hi> tho' not their <hi>individual acts of Worſhip:</hi> Or <hi>one in all the Rites and Modes of their Worſhip?</hi> If the firſt only be intended, all good Chriſtians are in Unity: I know of none but worſhip God by <hi>Prayer, Praiſes, receiving the Sacraments,</hi> &amp;c. Muſt it needs be an Union in all the Rites, and Modes of Worſhip?</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the firſt place, There was never ſuch an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> either in the <hi>Primitive Churches,</hi> or betwixt the <hi>Reformed Churches;</hi> Could they not therefore love another?</p>
            <p>2. If there muſt be ſuch an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> for which I ſee no reaſon, What Church ſhall be the Standard to which all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42746:7"/> others ſhall Unite? Why ſhould the Church of God in <hi>Scotland</hi> more Unite to that in <hi>England,</hi> than that in <hi>England</hi> to that in <hi>Scotland?</hi> Shall the Word of God over-rule? Then all are bound to Unite to that Church which performs all its Acts of Worſhip moſt conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to the Divine Rule. To this I know no <hi>Diſſenter</hi> but will willingly ſay, Amen.</p>
            <p>4. But it is yet much more un-intelligible, how Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians (not joyning with others in the ſame Modes, and Rites of Worſhip) ſhould be in effect a declaring them to be as Heathens and Publicans, and Perſons out of a ſtate of Salvation. This,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the firſt place proclaims to the World, that thoſe that are of this Mind not joyning with <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> in publick <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Praiſes,</hi> and in the Sacraments, is <hi>in effect</hi> a <hi>declaring them Heathens and Publicans, and not in a ſtate of Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I cannot underſtand the Divinity of this Aſſertion. May not Chriſtians chuſe to joyn in Communion with one Congregation, and adhere to that alone, and yet think others Chriſtians, and in a ſtate of Salvation? this is certainly both a new, and falſe Notion. It is not enough for to juſtifie me to joyn with other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that Salvation may be had amongſt them. I am further obliged to joyn my ſelf with ſuch where the Ordinances are ſo adminiſtred as my Conſcience tells me will be moſt to my comfort, and Edification, and as I judge, is neareſt to the Divine Rule. I know that in all caſes a Chriſtian is not always obliged to do what is beſt, but that in the Worſhip of God he is not ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged, is more than I, or I ſuppoſe any thinking Divine will aſſert. But I have dwelt upon this too long. He who doth not think himſelf and his Church <hi>Infallible,</hi> may eaſily allow others to be Chriſtians, and in a ſtate of Salvation, that do not in ſome Rites and Modes (of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42746:8"/> which the Word of God ſaith nothing) follow him, and thoſe with whom he chuſeth to walk. If any do think themſelves infallible, and fit to make a <hi>Standard</hi> to the World, they certainly think of themſelves, above what they ought to think, or can think with any degree of Humility. I conclude, That it is the Duty of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians (agreed in things neceſſary to Salvation) to be at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> one with another ſo far, as mutually to Unite all their Councels and Studies, and Practices in things which concern the Glory of God, and the common good of the place wherein they dwell together, tho' they may differ in ſome private Opinions, and ſuch differences may oblige them not to walk together, in thoſe things wherein they are not agreed, and to be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to do all good offices one to another, both <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, maintaining what they apprehend (tho' differently) to be Truth in Love, and <hi>ſerving one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in love.</hi> Nor is there a greater difficulty in this, than what attends all <hi>Self Denial,</hi> without which we cannot be the Diſciples of Chriſt, who ſo can deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in <hi>malice,</hi> and <hi>hatred</hi> againſt ſuch as he judgeth ſtricter than himſelf, and in <hi>Pride,</hi> thinking that it is poſſible he may be miſtaken, may eaſily overcome this difficulty; which is no more than every one muſt meet with, that will come in Heaven. Though <hi>Calvin</hi> would not joyn in Communion with <hi>Luther,</hi> yet he not only loved him, but own'd him <hi>as an eminent Servant</hi> of God, and profeſs'd he would ſo acknowledge him, <hi>though he ſhould call him a Devil,</hi> (ſuch was the Sweetneſs and Evangelicalneſs of that excellent Man's temper) This I ſay, is our Duty to be as the Apoſtle phraſeth it, <hi>Rom. 12. 10. Kindly affectioned one to another in love;</hi> But it is not my Buſineſs to demonſtrate this (tho' it were very eaſie) but my work is to ſhew you the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of ſuch a dwelling together. The Text ſaith it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42746:8"/> is <hi>happy</hi> and <hi>pleaſant;</hi> About the latter I ſhall not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: The <hi>pleaſantneſs</hi> of ſuch a <hi>dwelling together,</hi> is obvious to ſence; to ſee any Society of Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ready to ſpend, and be ſpent for one another, to <hi>ſerve one another in love in all mutual Offices,</hi> is pleaſant to every Eye, but that which is envious, which nothing pleaſeth that is another's good. I ſhall make it my only buſineſs to demonſtrate the Happineſs of ſuch a Life, which I ſhall do in ſeveral Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is <hi>the only Humane Life.</hi> A Life of diſcord, and diviſion, biting and devouring one another, continual Feuds and Quarrels, is a <hi>Brutal Life.</hi> Amongſt living Creatures, ſome are under the meer conduct of <hi>Senſe and Appetite,</hi> ſuch are the Beaſts of the Field; Others (ſuch is Man) are under the conduct of reaſon and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of that, which God hath planted in Man to rule and govern his ſenſitive appetite, and reſtrain it in thoſe Exorbitancies to which ſince the Fall it is very prone, and to reduce the Soul to its Primitive order; hence you ſee that divers Beaſts can hardly be one with another, or meet one with another, but they are grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning each at other, biting, or devouring, or puſhing one another; but with Men it is otherwiſe, and amongſt Men railing, and reviling, fighting, and quarrelling are generally found in the meaner ſort of Men not cultiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Education, or ill-bred. The only <hi>Humane Life</hi> is a Life of Amity and Unity. It ſpeaketh ſuch Men to have moſt recovered the Image of God in Man (ſo far as it concerns <hi>Reaſon.)</hi> And if it be any Happineſs to Men, to have recovered this, and to have attained to an ability to live like Perſons poſſeſt of reaſonable Souls: This Happineſs thoſe Brethren have who have learn't ſo far to deny their Luſts and Paſſions, as to live toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:42746:9"/>2. Secondly, <hi>It is the only</hi> good <hi>that extendeth it ſelf to many.</hi> We ſay in Philoſophy, that all Good is diffuſive, and by how much any thing is more common, or more communicative, the better it is. There is no ſuch thing in nature as a clung, hide-bound Good, that only feedeth upon it ſelf; or, if you will, <hi>It is</hi> the <hi>only</hi> good <hi>that is productive of Goodneſs:</hi> For if <hi>Dives</hi> fareth deliciouſly every day, if he hath not a bit of Meat, or a piece of Money to give a <hi>Lazarus,</hi> his Riches are <hi>no good</hi> (truly ſo call'd) at leaſt they are productive of no <hi>goodneſs</hi> at all. Now take all other things we call Good, they only ſerve ſingle Perſons, without this dwelling together in Unity, being kindly affectionated to, and freely ſerving one another in love. This is ſuch a Good, as is a fruitful Mother, which many call Bleſſed, becauſe it gives a Portion to ſix and alſo to ſeven. This is one thing by which the Pſalmiſt demonſtrates the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> when he compareth it <hi>to the precious Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the head, that ran down upon the beard, and did not wet</hi> Aaron's <hi>head alone, but ran down to the skirts of his Garment.</hi> Take all other things which we call <hi>good, Riches, Honour, Learning,</hi> they only give ſingle Perſons an Happineſs, and that very imperfect; this living together in an Union of Councels and Deſigns for one anothers welfare, and a being kindly affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated one to another, and ready to ſerve one another in love, is a <hi>common Good</hi> to all that live in ſuch an Union.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Third and greateſt demonſtration is in the laſt words of the Pſalm, <hi>There</hi> God <hi>commandeth the bleſſing.</hi> That is an happy Society upon which God commandeth the Bleſſing; but on theſe Societies it is that God commandeth his Bleſſings.</p>
            <p>The next Queſtion is, what Bleſſings they are which God commandeth upon Societies of Perſons dwelling to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42746:9"/> in ſuch an Unity, as I have been deſcribing to you; and here, <hi>—Inopem me copia fecit,</hi> I ſhall more eaſily know where to begin, than where to end. All Bleſſings that Mankind is capable of, refer either to the <hi>outward</hi> or to the <hi>inward Man;</hi> I ſhall diſcourſe both apart, beginning with thoſe that refer to the <hi>outward Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. And the firſt in <hi>Riches,</hi> and <hi>all outward Proſperity.</hi> This I take to be hinted by our <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in that Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, It is <hi>like the dew of Hermon, and as the dew that deſcended upon the Mountains of Zion;</hi> the Dew made the Mountains full of Graſs, Corn, Wine, and Oyl. We may apply to this <hi>dwelling together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> what <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 3. 16.</note> ſaith of <hi>Wiſdom; Length of days is in her right hand, and in her left hand Riches and Honour.</hi> The Health of the Body Natural depends upon the Unity of the Humours: and the Health of the Body Politick e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually depends upon the Union of the Members of it. It hath been obſerved, that where the Popiſh Inquiſition hath come, it hath ſpoiled all the Wealth and Trade of the place, the reaſon is, becauſe it hath ſpoiled the Unity of the whole, for the Unity of a part. On the contrary, where a Liberty hath been granted for Mens various Opinions in Religion and Practice ſuitably, thoſe places have abounded in Riches, (of which our Brethren in the Low Countries is a demonſtration very near us). And for this, a great deal of reaſon is to be given,</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the <hi>Will of God.</hi> Places where People live together in Unity, are places where God hath declared he will command the Bleſſing; now thoſe whom he bleſſeth ſhall be bleſſed. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith in one place, <hi>The diligent hand maketh rich;</hi> in another, <hi>Prov. 10. 22. The bleſſing of God maketh rich,</hi> and he <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no ſorrow therewith.</hi> The curſe of God, may make Rich, but Sorrow will be added to thoſe Riches: God
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42746:10"/> in the ordinary courſe of his Providence, doth not bleſs a People with Riches that live in Diſcord, and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually biting and devouring of one another.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond Reaſon may be, <hi>The Contribution which <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity makes to Riches.</hi> Riches ordinarily are gotten by ſome Trade and Dealing with others; now no Man tradeth alone, there is (as I think <hi>Cicero</hi> calls it) <hi>quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam connexio rationum,</hi> a connexion of ſeveral Mens ways of living, which muſt make up a Trade; and this (to become profitable) requires ſo much Boldneſs, and mutual Confidence, as can be in no place where Men do not dwell together in Unity: and this muſt be true, as to all that part of Trade which is at home. Beſides, where Men live together in Diſcord, and Enmity, all their Studies are to ruin and devour one another with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Pity, (we have had too late an Experience of it for ſome years) and it is the keener, and more edged, where one Party can be perſwaded, that in what they do, they do God Service, and the mad cry can be raiſed for the <hi>Holy houſe</hi> (as it is in ſome Popiſh Countries) it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently puts the People in uproar, and no man is ſecure, becauſe, <hi>Great is</hi> Diana <hi>of the</hi> Epheſians. On the other ſide, where Men live together in Unity, every one trades freely according to his Talent, and is not afraid of a <hi>Gaol,</hi> whiles he lives juſtly and honeſtly, every Man wiſheth well to his Neighbour, helps, adviſeth, aſſiſteth him, repoſeth mutual Confidence in him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There is a Precept of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 24. than which there is none more uſeful to Mankind, <hi>Let every man not ſeek his own, but anothers wealth;</hi> that is, not his own only: and where it is not put in practice, a ſhort time makes a City a Corporation of Beggars; for there muſt be more than one, to make one thrive, where there is <hi>Diſcord, Hatred, Envy, Malice,</hi> ſeeking advantages againſt, <hi>biting, devouring of one another;</hi> few or none
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42746:10"/> grow rich, but ſuch as live by ill Arts, upon the Spoils of others, and thoſe are ſuch ill Plants in a Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as the juſtice of God ſeldom will allow to grow to any heighth, where Men dwell together in this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> every Man is as a Journyman to his Neighbour, and lending him his hands to be rich. You ſee it in a ſmall Society of Friends, there always attendeth it, a being <hi>kindly affectionated one to another,</hi> a <hi>forbearing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in love,</hi> a <hi>ſerving one another.</hi> So many true Friends as a Man hath, ſo many Servants he hath. <hi>Concordia parvae res creſcunt,</hi> little Eſtates grow great by it. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords nouriſh none but Birds of Prey, that can digeſt the Blood and Fleſh of others.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond Bleſſing conſequent to this Brethrens dwelling together in Unity, is <hi>comfortable Society</hi> and fellowſhip. This is the life of Mens lives, for Man is a ſociable Creature, and as it is not good for him to be alone, ſo naturally he loves it not. How miſerable doth that Man judge himſelf, who is ſhut up in a Priſon where none muſt come at him? Experience tells us how miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the life of Perſons in a Family is, for want of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal, Parental, and Filial love; and if you go out of thoſe Doors, you will find it the ſame, for want of <hi>Neighbourly love.</hi> Two may <hi>walk together</hi> tho' they be not agreed; but it will be no pleaſant walk. There is no Pleaſure in a litigious ſnarling Society; but how ſweet is the Society of Perſons kindly affectionated one toward another, and ready upon all occaſions to ſerve one another?</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third more external Bleſſing is <hi>mutual</hi> and <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial aſſiſtance.</hi> God hath created us in a Connexion with, and a dependancy upon one another: In my courſe of life in the World, I have made this obſervation; I never yet knew a Prince ſo great, but at one time or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath found that he hath had need of his Peoples
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42746:11"/> Hands, and Purſes; nor private Perſon ſo ſufficient to himſelf, but he hath had need of his pooreſt Neighbours: This requireth <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> amongſt Brethren. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>Eccleſ. 4. 10. Two are better than one; for if one falleth, the other will lift him up: but wo to him that is alone, for if he falleth, he hath none to lift him up. If two lye together, they ſhall have heat, but how can one be warm that is alone?</hi> and if one prevail againſt <hi>him two ſhall withſtand him, and a threefold Cord is not quickly broken.</hi> The many <hi>Companies</hi> and <hi>Partnerſhips,</hi> with which the World, abounds in carrying on Buſineſs of Trades, are a ſufficient proof of this.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A fourth more outward Bleſſing, is <hi>Stability</hi> and <hi>Conſiſtency.</hi> The abiding of all compounded Bodies doth very much depend upon the union of their ſeveral parts one with another. Thus it is in the Body Natural, thus it is in Buildings, thus it muſt be in all Compoſitions. Thus it is in Bodies Politick, <hi>Math. 12. 25. The houſe divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand.</hi> Let the condition of a State, a Kingdom, any Society, be never ſo flouriſhing, it cannot abide longer than the Union of the principal Parts of it do abide: <hi>Vis unita fortior,</hi> A firm Union of ſeveral things of the ſame kind, makes all their Strength and Virtues one; and many Eyes ſee more than one, and many Hands can do more than one; hence is the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the Proſperity of all ſuch Societies, which is a great Bleſſing. I will add but one more.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That ſhall be <hi>Succeſs in Buſineſs.</hi> Diſcord clogs the wheels of all publick Councels and Actions: Let it be Buſineſs of War, or Peace, of what nature ſoever it be for a publick good, it muſt move ſlowly and with ſmall ſucceſs, whiles thoſe concerned in it, have divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Ends and Counſels, and draw diverſe ways. I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that when God promiſed Proſperity and Succeſs to his ancient People, in order to it, he promiſed that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42746:11"/> the <hi>ſtick for the houſe of Judah,</hi> and the ſtick for the <hi>houſe of Joſeph</hi> ſhould be <hi>made one ſtick,</hi> Ezek. 37. 16, 17, 18. This is enough to ſhew you what external Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings God commands, where Brethren dwell together in the Unity I have deſcribed.</p>
            <p>But yet the flood of Spiritual Bleſſings commanded, and brought by this dwelling together in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> is much greater, and much more valuable. Let me open this in a few particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It is the only Chriſtian life.</hi> A life of Unity, is not only the life of a Man who is endued with a reaſonable Soul, and ſhould walk under the conduct, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, but it is the <hi>life of a Chriſtian,</hi> who by his Name is obliged to <hi>fulfil the Law of Chriſt,</hi> and not to walk <hi>after the fleſh,</hi> but <hi>after the ſpirit.</hi> No Man or Woman can live up to the Law of Chriſt, but he, or ſhe, that dwells with their Brethren in Unity. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaking of himſelf and others, whiles they were in a ſtate of unregeneracy, deſcribeth their life thus, <hi>Tit. 3. 3. We our ſelves</hi> were ſometimes fooliſh, diſobedient, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, ſerving <hi>divers luſts, and pleaſures, living in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and envy, hateful and hating one another.</hi> The Law of God is a Law of Love and Unity, and further exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive than to thoſe that <hi>follow us. Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf</hi> (ſaid the old Law, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.) and the Law of Chriſt is the <hi>Royal Law of Love. This is my Commandment</hi> (ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Joh. 15.) that you love one another.</hi> The Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. reckoneth up the <hi>fruits of the fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>fruits of the Spirit,</hi> he tells you the <hi>works of the fleſh</hi> are—v. 20. <hi>Hatred, Variance, Wrath, Strife,</hi> v. 22. the fruit of the Spirit, is <hi>Love, Peace.</hi> If it be the Happineſs of any People, to have recovered the Image of God, and to be arrived at the life of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, this Happineſs they are arrived at, that dwell together in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42746:12"/>2. It is a life in which a <hi>world of Sins,</hi> (and thoſe the blackeſt of Sins) <hi>are avoided.</hi> No People live with leſs guilt of Sin upon their Souls, than thoſe that are ſo far reconciled to the whole Creation, as to be kindly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionated one to another in love, and ready in love to ſerve one another in love. By this <hi>Pride</hi> is avoided, by which alone <hi>cometh contention</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon)</hi> Love ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues that a Man thinks of himſelf as he ought to think, as a poor fallible Perſon, that may be miſtaken as well as his Neighbour, and therefore can love his Neighbour tho' he be not in all things of his Mind, and doth not in all things follow him. <hi>Envy, malice, hatred, thinking evil of, and wiſhing evil to his Neighbour</hi> are all avoided by this dwelling together in Unity. Since we in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have broke looſe from this Rule, obſerve into what Exorbitances we have fallen, and debauched our ſelves to a degree, hardly to be believed of Chriſtians; from hence have come our new phraſed Healths to the <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Confuſion</hi> of others. <hi>(Bleſſed God!</hi> were ever ſuch things heard of before amongſt a People that ever owned <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or his Goſpel?) But it is no wonder that Men who have not ſo far learned Chriſt as to <hi>love one another,</hi> but think every little difference in an Opinion, or Practice a ſufficient ground to hate another, ſhould be ſo far taught by the <hi>Devil,</hi> as to <hi>hate one another,</hi> and wiſh the worſt of Evils to them, contrary to all Rules of <hi>Humanity</hi> as well as <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> Let me fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther add, theſe are not only Sins, but of all Sins the blackeſt, next to Blaſphemy againſt God, and his Holy Spirit. Our Saviour, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. hath taught us, that they fall under the Prohibition of that Precept. <hi>Thou ſhalt do no Murther,</hi> and his beloved Diſciple tells us after him, <hi>That he who hateth his Brother, is a Murtherer,</hi> and no Murtherer <hi>hath Eternal life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:42746:12"/>3. <hi>By this life much advantage is taken away from our grand Adverſary.</hi> The Apoſtle tells us, 1 <hi>Pet. 5. 8. Our Adverſary the Devil, goeth about like a roaring Lion, ſeeking whom he may devour.</hi> He is a cruel Adverſary, therefore compared to <hi>a Lion, a roaring Lion,</hi> one <hi>ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whom he may devour;</hi> He is a <hi>diligent Adverſary,</hi> not like a Lion in his Den, that needs one to rouſe him up, he is <hi>up</hi> going about and ſeeking for his Prey; yea, he is alſo a ſubtil Adverſary, that hath <hi>Wiles, Methods, Devices:</hi> nor doth he take a greater advantage of any thing, than the <hi>coilings of our Paſſions.</hi> The Apoſtle was jealous of his taking advantage of the <hi>Corinthians, 2 Cor.</hi> 2. 11. upon this account he there adviſeth the <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 11.</note> reſtoring the inceſtuous Perſon upon his <hi>Repentance.</hi> If you ask me what Advantages the Devil is ſpoiled of, by this life of Unity? I anſwer, all the Advantages that he hath from <hi>hatred,</hi> to move us to do unto others what we would not be willing they ſhould do us, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Word or Deed. It is the Precept of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 1 <hi>Tim. 5. 14. Give no occaſion to the Adverſary.</hi> The <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 14.</note> Evil Spirits diſcerning the want of love in us giveth him a fair advantage to tempt us to <hi>revile, nickname</hi> him, wound his Reputation, to <hi>rejoice in Evil</hi> betiding him, to ſpoil him of his Goods, his Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Fourthly,</p>
            <p n="4">4. This living together in Unity, <hi>opens a door for great ſpiritual advantage one to another.</hi> I will open this but in Four things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It is the neareſt way, to bring us to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Opinion, and ſo to a perfect communion each with other.</hi> We have been theſe many years, complaining of <hi>Separation,</hi> calling for <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> But what courſes have we taken to bring it about? Each Party hath been diſputing for his differing Notion: and where this hath been done nervouſly and calmly, the moſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional means hath been uſed, but we have ſeen little
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42746:13"/> good effect of it, by reaſon of Mens <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice,</hi> we have rather contended for <hi>Maſtery</hi> than for <hi>Truth.</hi> Another parcel of Men have fell to <hi>railing</hi> and <hi>reviling,</hi> calling Men <hi>Schiſmaticks, Hereticks, Papiſts, Formaliſts;</hi> now this hath been juſt as proper a means to bring Men to dwell together in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> as it would be to perſuade others to live in the ſame Houſe with us to call them Knaves, and give them all the <hi>brutiſh Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage</hi> we could, Of late we have thought nothing would do it but <hi>Violence,</hi> and accordingly we have been filling Gaols, rifling Houſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus the <hi>Spaniard</hi> hath got an Unity where he hath to do, by depopulating his Country. Had we in ſtead of theſe <hi>fiery counſels,</hi> but agreed in this, That whether we agreed in every No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or no, or met at the ſame place to worſhip God by the ſame <hi>Rites,</hi> yea, or no, we would unite in Counſels for the <hi>Glory of God,</hi> and the <hi>good of the Community</hi> in which we are involved, and be ready to do all offices of <hi>love one to another,</hi> we might by this time have bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtood one another, and all that truly agreed in the ſame end of glorifying God, would (probably long ere this time) have agreed in the directeſt means in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereunto. I am ſure we have hitherto took the wrong way to peace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It would open a great Door for the <hi>converſion of others.</hi> I do not mean Converſion <hi>to an Opinion</hi> (that's a lamentable thing) but <hi>converſion from Sin unto God.</hi> Upon this Argument, the great Apoſtle of the Gentiles perſuades the <hi>believing Wife to abide with the unbeliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Husband,</hi> and the <hi>believing Husband to abide with the unbelieving Wife. What knowſt thou, O Wife, but that thou may'ſt ſave thy Husband?</hi> &amp;c. God is love, and ſo much the God of love, and the worſt Men have ſo right a Notion of God in this caſe, That they cannot believe God is amongſt a Society of Men, where is nothing but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42746:13"/> fighting and ſcratching, railing at, and reviling of one another, who yet are in Religion Brethren.</p>
            <p>It maketh ſome ſo Mad, that they will rather chooſe to go to <hi>Hell</hi> than to Heaven with ſuch Company (as they ſay the <hi>Indian</hi> did, rather than to keep the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard</hi> company to Heaven). Offices of Love are a great part of thoſe good Works to which the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 12.</note> exhorts, <hi>that others may ſee them, and glorifie God in the day of their Viſitation.</hi> The <hi>Papiſts</hi> (who have as little reaſon as any to boaſt of it) make <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> the note of a true Church. The truth is, they have no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> but what is the product of <hi>Tyranny.</hi> I doubt not but there is many a Soul in Heaven, to whom the ancient brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly love amongſt Chriſtians, was a great means to bring them thither: and many a Soul in Hell, to whom the diſcords and violences of Chriſtians one againſt another, hath been a great occaſion of their keeping in that broad Way that leads to that bottomleſs pit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>It opens a Door for all thoſe mutual ſpiritual aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances by which one Chriſtian may be advantaged by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> whether they be <hi>Inſtructions, Counſels, Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Reproofs,</hi> &amp;c. That they are our Duty, appears from <hi>Coloſ. 3. 16. Gal. 6. 1. 2 Theſſ.</hi> 3. 15. Now where Men dwell not together in that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> I have deſcribed, little or nothing of this is done, at leaſt with any good ſucceſs, and effect; he that apprehends himſelf hated by his Brother, will not be very patiently reproved, or admoniſhed, or inſtructed by him: but he who findeth his Brother loves him, yields an <hi>obedient Ear</hi> to a <hi>wiſe reproof,</hi> and ſaith with <hi>David, Pſal. 141. 5. Let the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſmite me, it ſhall be a Kindneſs, and let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove me, it ſhall be an excellent Oil, which ſhall not break my Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, It gives <hi>the great advantage of mutual Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers one for another.</hi> Thoſe Prophane Perſons, that drink
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42746:14"/> to the <hi>Damnation, Confuſion, Deſtruction</hi> of others, let you know how they pray for one another, that do not dwell together in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> Now as little as the irreligious part of the World judge to be of advantage from the Prayers of others, it appeareth <hi>Paul</hi> was not of their Mind, by his ſo often begging the Chriſtians Prayers who were many degrees his Inferiours. The Apoſtle preſſeth the Duty of <hi>Husbands</hi> to their <hi>Wives</hi> upon this <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 7.</note> Argument, <hi>That your Prayers be not hindred.</hi> It is a great Evil to any Society of Chriſtians, that hindreth their Prayers one for another: and by a Parity of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whatever promoveth, and advantageth ſuch Prayers, muſt be a great good, and of a great advantage. But I ſhall dwell no longer upon the Doctrinal part of my Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. This Notion in the firſt place may ſerve to convince you, how great a cauſe you have this day to meet, and <hi>give Thanks to the God of Heaven.</hi> It is true, there are two ways, either of which if you look, you will ſee reaſon to <hi>Rejoice with trembling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>If you look upon the Enemies which we have abroad.</hi> There is no doubt but that <hi>Nimrod,</hi> that <hi>mighty hunter before the Lord,</hi> who hath driven all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> out of his <hi>Dominions,</hi> hath as good a mind to drive them all out of the World; and there is as little doubt but that there are abundance of <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> who make it their deſign in all places where they lurk.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And it is as melancholick a Proſpect <hi>if we look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sins of the Nation,</hi> and the Numbers of ſuch, all whoſe Proteſtant Religion lyes in their <hi>Proteſting</hi> againſt any <hi>Reformation.</hi> I ſay, if we look at this, we may ſee ſome cauſe to ſay, Can a pure and Holy God ſpare ſo prophane, ſo vile, and ſinful a People as this? Shall not our Earth diſcloſe her Blood? Shall it cover her ſlain In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents? Our Fears are not over, nor is our ſtate ſecure.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42746:14"/> There is yet room for <hi>Faſting and Prayer,</hi> and bitter mourning before the Lord, if the bitter Cup may poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly paſs over.</p>
            <p>But we have this Day at leaſt three eminent, and undeniable Cauſes of Thankſgiving.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That ſo great a Revolution of Divine Providence is thus far paſſed over, with ſo ſmall a ſhower of Blood.</hi> Very few Weeks have paſſed, ſince every of our Hands were upon our Loins, and we ſtood in a trembling Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what would be the iſſue of that great Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which we ſaw. The Effuſion of much Proteſtants Blood was the leaſt of our Expectations, the dreadful conſequent of a Victory by Blood with reference to the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt</hi> over all the World, was a much more terrifying Speculation. Now that God ſhould do what is done with the ſhedding of ſo little Blood, certainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth their Thankſgivings, who have any Kindneſs for the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Deliverance of the Nation from ſo great degree of fear, as the moſt were under as to their beſt, and higheſt Concern is another thing.</hi> I know <hi>Popery</hi> had not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran us, nor was it the topping Religion of the Nation, nor like to have been in a ſhort tract of Time. But we know that there is in us all a deſire to Propagate our own Sentiments in Religion, and we cannot but judge that Princes who have more Power, have greater Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, tho not adviſed by ſuch as are reſtleſs in ſuch a deſign. God indeed hath ſo far bleſſed the Preaching of the Goſpel, that the moſt Peoples Palats are ſpoiled for ſuch <hi>Lamp Oil,</hi> as their Doctrines of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation, Purgatory,</hi> and many other abſurd tenets of that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: nor was <hi>England</hi> to be <hi>hewed</hi> into a Conformity to them, by ſuch <hi>wooden Tools,</hi> as came to do it, they muſt have been Perſons of more <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> too that could have promiſed themſelves any ſudden Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42746:15"/> Nor were their Numbers any way proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for any ſuch work as their Converſion of three Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in their uſual Methods of Converſion by <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Sword;</hi> But we muſt have lived in fear of ſuch a diſmal change, and died in a greater for our Poſterity. From theſe (bleſſed be God) we are in a great meaſure deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and the Bondage of Fear is no inconſiderable Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage. This alſo giveth us an apparent Cauſe of Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, <hi>That we may now ſerve the Lord without fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. But there is yet a third, and poſſibly that not the leaſt cauſe of rejoycing before the Lord this day, <hi>viz. That we have now the faireſt opportunity offered us for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Proteſtants in theſe Nations, amongſt themſelves, and with our Brethren of other reformed Churches that ever our Eyes ſaw, and beyond whatever our Forefathers could could tell us of.</hi> I mean by the Excluſion of the <hi>Romiſh Party,</hi> from any influence upon our <hi>Courts</hi> and <hi>Councels,</hi> whoſo readeth the Hiſtory of our <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Affairs</hi> for 130 years laſt paſt, may ſee juſt reaſon to admire, that inſtead of making further ſteps forward we have ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeemed to have gone backward. In Doctrine indeed we had a very conſiderable <hi>Reformation,</hi> and ſo in <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> in <hi>Diſcipline</hi> very little, and that directed by ſome particular <hi>Statutes,</hi> tho' that was by our firſt <hi>Reformers</hi> as truly intended as the other, and at leaſt 4 Acts of Parliament made to Authorize the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England</hi> to appoint <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> for it, and ſomething was done of that Nature, but that bleſſed <hi>Prince</hi> Edw. 6. died be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had given it his <hi>Royal Sanction;</hi> ſince whoſe time, nothing hath been done in it; this we are told hath been by the mighty influence upon our <hi>Court,</hi> which the <hi>Romiſh Party</hi> had, who poſſibly might labour to keep up their old <hi>Forms of Diſcipline,</hi> ſo far as our <hi>Statute</hi> Laws, and <hi>King</hi>'s Prerogative would allow them, if peradventure they might ever gain an opportunity to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42746:15"/> uſe them to ſerve their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urns: This hath been one great Cauſe of our <hi>Diviſions</hi> of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> amongſt themſelves. Another bitter root hath been in <hi>Matters of Worſhip.</hi> In the beginning of our <hi>Reformation</hi> ſo much of the ancient <hi>Forms, Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> were retained, (as was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to gain the <hi>Papiſts</hi> into our Communion. This did ſomething, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> firſt years of Queen <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> but when their <hi>Holy Father</hi> commanded the contrary, it would do no longer. <hi>Then Laws muſt be made to force them into it,</hi> and theſe ſo penned, that they might equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerve to force in all <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and as more Laws were made (occaſion'd by the Treaſons of the <hi>Romiſh Party)</hi> ſtill, ſuch Words and Phraſes were got in, as made them (at leaſt in the Judgment of ſome Judges) applicable to <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> At laſt it came to it, that they were executed with much more <hi>ſeverity</hi> againſt <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> than againſt <hi>Papiſts.</hi> This alſo was charged upon the <hi>Influence of a Popiſh Party,</hi> had upon our <hi>Court,</hi> and <hi>Councels.</hi> Well, God hath by a ſtupendious Providence delivered us from any ſuch Influence; ſo that I ſay, here is a larger Door for this Unity offered, than ever we or our Fathers ſaw, and this is a great Bleſſing worthy to be accepted with all thankfulneſs, if this <hi>dwelling together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> be ſo great an Happineſs as I have ſhewed you it is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. What therefore remains, but that I ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade all you that hear me this day <hi>to diſpoſe your ſelves to ſo great a piece of Happineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In order to this, I ſhall offer you 3 or 4 Arguments, and then conclude with a few words of advice, &amp; counſel.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I beſeech you to <hi>reflect upon the Opportunities we have already loſt:</hi> There are two more eminent within the Memory of many that hear me. <hi>That in the year</hi> 1660. when all the Nation was united in their <hi>Supreme Governour</hi> reſtored in a moſt ſtupendious manner. One
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42746:16"/> would have thought, that the Experience of 20 years Calamities much occaſioned from our <hi>Religious Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> might then have prompted all, to utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to Unite all Proteſtants; but inſtead of it, we made ſo ill an uſe of that Opportunity, that our Diviſions were vaſtly increaſed by it. 'Tis too ſad a Story to be too particular in. A ſecond was Ten years ſince, upon the Diſcovery of the <hi>Pupiſh Plot:</hi> we heard then, that all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> were equally called <hi>Hereticks.</hi> That our <hi>Biſhopricks, Deanries,</hi> were diſpoſed of to Men of the <hi>Romiſh perſuaſion:</hi> Was it not then time to unite all <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> we loſt that opportunity likewiſe, and after that, the Deſigns were more, and the Zeal hotter than ever, to root out all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> who could not unite in the <hi>eſtabliſh'd Forms of Worſhip and Diſcipline.</hi> The loſs of both theſe Opportunities, hath alſo been char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon the potent Influence Men of the <hi>Romiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> had upon our <hi>Court and Councels,</hi> and 'tis certain their Influence was great, how far they uſed it to this end, I cannot tell. For my own part, I had given over <hi>England</hi> for loſt, at leaſt the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niting of Proteſtants</hi> for loſt. I deſpaired of ſeeing any thing would ſave thoſe whom ſo miraculous a Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auration and a Deliverance from ſo pernicious and general a Plot would not ſave. God hath out-done my hopes and expectation, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us a third Opportunity. If we loſe this too, <hi>The Interpretation be to them that hate us, and to the Enemies of our God, and Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly Let me deſire you to reflect upon the <hi>ſad Conſequents</hi> of the loſs of <hi>thoſe two firſt mentioned op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities.</hi> A firſt and ſecond War with our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Holland</hi> (next us, the only Bulwark of our Religion) ſuch a Plague as we nor our Fathers ever knew. The burning of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and many other Towns and Cities. The ruining of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands for Nonconformity.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:42746:16"/>
            <p>What were <hi>the Conſequents of our</hi> letting ſlip the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond opportunity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the cruel, and harbarous uſages of thoſe that dared to tell our <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Parliament,</hi> that there were thoſe had conſpired their ruin, the death of divers worthy Perſons, the Finings and Impriſonments of others, the Subverting the <hi>Governments of Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> the Interpreting Laws to a ſenſe never before heard of, on purpoſe to ruin a great Party of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If we ſhould loſe a third opportunity, we may eaſily Propheſie the Conſequents are like to be much more <hi>fatal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, <hi>Let the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of your Enemies move you.</hi> The <hi>Papiſts</hi> are hardly United ſo much in any one thing, as their <hi>good will,</hi> and <hi>zeal</hi> to deſtroy us, whom they call <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and indeed we worſhip the God of our Fathers after the way they call Hereſie. Shall not we Unite to preſerve our ſelves?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, Let me tell you, <hi>this will be a real Thankſgiving;</hi> other praiſing God is but <hi>in word, and in Tongue only,</hi> but loving one another is the command of our Lord, productive of a great deal of good, and glory to God, and impeditive of a World of ſin.</p>
            <p>You will all grant me this, but you will ſay, How may this thing be? or what may we do in order to the arriving at ſuch an happineſs? In the general: As there is nothing but our receding from the divine Rule, which hath cauſed our <hi>Diviſions,</hi> ſo there is nothing but a return to that Rule which will ever bring us to an U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Our <hi>Diviſions</hi> have been partly in matters of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> towards God, partly in our <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> and <hi>Political Converſation</hi> towards men; and the former, have not a little inflamed and advantaged the latter: I will therefore moſt in large with reference to the former; and ſhew you, how the Deviation from the divine Rule hath been the cauſe of thoſe Diſcords. I will inſtance in five or ſix particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:42746:17"/>1. The firſt ſhall be <hi>Superiors making thoſe things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary by their Commands, which they themſelves own to be in their own Nature indifferent, and this in matters of Worſhip and Religion.</hi> That in caſe the Superior judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a thing <hi>neceſſary,</hi> he ought to command it, thoſe that are under his Juriſdiction is on all hands granted. What he apprehends by God commanded to be done or for born in matters of his Worſhip, he muſt command or forbid, for he is Gods Vicegerent, and ought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force his Laws, tho' the Subject hath other apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of it, and tho' it may be the Superior be miſtaken in his Notion, for he muſt Act according to the dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates of his own Conſcience, and in this caſe the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior who judgeth otherwiſe, hath nothing to do but patiently to ſuffer. In <hi>Civil things,</hi> tho' the thing be in it ſelf <hi>indifferent,</hi> yet the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> may command it, becauſe he judgeth it <hi>neceſſary</hi> or <hi>expedient</hi> for his <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Government.</hi> And he is Judge of ſuch <hi>neceſſity</hi> or <hi>expedience,</hi> not the Inferior, but it is otherwiſe in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, there is no Judge Superior to a Mans Conſcience but God alone. God in his word hath not left ſufficient particular directions for the upholding and well beings of States and Kingdoms, but he hath left us only general Rules for <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Equity,</hi> and made the Magiſtrate judge of things <hi>neceſſary</hi> or not <hi>neceſſary, expedient</hi> or <hi>inexpedient</hi> as to that, and clothed him with a Power to <hi>make</hi> and <hi>execute Laws</hi> in order to that end. In Matters of Religion, and Worſhip, God hath left ſufficient Rules in his Worſhip for the Preſervation, and Government of his Church, and for all Chriſtians to pay homage to him, which he will accept, performed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to them, nor is there any thing further neceſſary, but the common Circumſtances of all Humane Actions to be applied to thoſe Religious Acts; neither is there any thing ſo indifferent, but may by ſome Circumſtances
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42746:17"/> become unlawful, either to greater numbers, or to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons in regard of their different apprehenſions of it. The Superiour is as much obliged by the Law of charity, as the Inferiour, and cannot ſet a ſtep in that way wherein he cannot <hi>walk charitably.</hi> Beſides, Chriſtians obſervation, that there is no preſident either in the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> or <hi>New,</hi> of Superiours either in Church or State, taking away that liberty of people which God had left them in matters relating to their homage to God, is no ſmall Topick to perſuade them that as the Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our hath <hi>no right</hi> to do it, ſo if they ſhould ſubmit to it they ſhould too eaſily part with <hi>that Liberty, which God hath left them,</hi> and with which <hi>Chriſt hath made them free.</hi> This makes this thing neceſſary to a Churches unity &amp; peace, and the not leaving things of this nature in that ſtate wherein it hath ſeemed good to the wiſdom of God to leave them in, this ſeems a deviation from the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Rule. Becauſe it is a deviation from the practice of all the <hi>good Kings of Gods ancient people,</hi> and the practice of <hi>Paul</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who inſtead of determining the liberty God gave the <hi>Jews</hi> for a time, as to the practice or not practice of the <hi>ceremonial uſages</hi> ſtrongly aſſerted it, and reflected upon thoſe converted <hi>Jews</hi> that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned ſome of their brethren, or the Chriſtians of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> for their uſing ſuch a liberty. This very thing hath been a bone of contention amongſt us for more than an hundred years, nor do I ſee any way to our unity, but our return to the Divine Rule in this thing; Superiours have a full work, and more than we could ever ſee uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally well done, to inforce the commands of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on people that will not take upon them thoſe eaſy yokes, and need not incumber themſelves or their Subjects con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, where it hath pleaſed the all-wiſe God to leave them at liberty. A man may <hi>keep a day holy to the Lord, and give God thanks,</hi> another may <hi>not keep it to the Lord,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:42746:18"/> 
               <hi>and yet give God thanks.</hi> (The Apoſtle determines ſo) when God hath left men two ways by either of which they may equally honour God, why ſhould men leave them but one? Juſt <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> are inſeparable things, as well in matters of <hi>Religion</hi> as in <hi>civil matters;</hi> Oh! that this thing ſo much concerning our peace, might not upon this opportunity be <hi>hid from our Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A Second thing whereby we have fomented divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions by a deviation from the Divine Rule, is by <hi>judging and cenſuring anothers Servants. Who art thou</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 14. 4.) that judgeſt another mans Servant?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 4.</note> 
               <hi>To his own Maſter he ſtandeth or falleth.</hi> In civil, and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar things, men may be the Servants of men, but in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Conſcience men are only the Servants of God; <hi>the fear of God</hi> muſt not be <hi>learned by the mere precepts of men,</hi> what a common thing hath it been with us, to judge and cenſure our brethren in theſe caſes, as <hi>Schiſmaticks, ungovernable, rebellious, &amp;c?</hi> Thoſe that uſe theſe methods have not <hi>known the way of peace.</hi> And till we return to the Apoſtles rule, <hi>Rom. 14. 13. Let us not therefore judge one</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 13.</note> 
               <hi>another any more, but judge this rather, that no man put a ſtumbling Block or an occaſion to fall in his Brothers way;</hi> I can look for no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi> When we can leave judging and cenſuring, reviling, and ſpeaking evil of our Brethren, of the ſame Religion, and Nation, as going in the broad way to Hell, becauſe they go in a narrower way toward Heaven than we judge neceſſary, or becauſe they juſt tread not in the prints of our Feet, (obſerving ſtill their faces Sion ward) we may hope for ſomething of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> But while ſuch uncharitable thoughts, and ſpeeches con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue amongſt us, as if we had a monopoly of the Holy Spirit of God, I cannot but expect they ſhould naturally produce all kind of uncharitable actions. Oh! that we could remember what the Apoſtle hath taught us, <hi>Jam</hi> 4. <note place="margin">Jam. 4. 12.</note> 12. that in matters of Conſcience. <hi>There is but one Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:42746:18"/> 
               <hi>who is able to ſave, and to deſtroy;</hi> and <hi>who art thou that judgeſt another?</hi> If we would but ſee it, we have moſt of us ſomething of the worſt of <hi>Popery</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us, <hi>viz.</hi> arrogating to our ſelves an <hi>infallibility</hi> with this difference to our diſadvantage. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> claim it only for the <hi>Pope.</hi> We would every one have it for our ſelves, or at leaſt for all Superiours, for if thou beeſt not infallible, how comeſt thou to judge thy Brother, who hath as much right to judge thee, as thou haſt to judge, and cenſure him. The Judgment of <hi>Prophaneneſs, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery, Blaſphemy, Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Hereſy</hi> too (in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters neceſſary to be believed in order to Salvation) is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; but the Judgment of <hi>Schiſm, Hypocriſie,</hi> overmuch <hi>preciſeneſs</hi> is not ſo eaſie. The guilt of thoſe things, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends much upon the Complexion of the particular Conſcience, and ſhould be left unto him who ſearcheth the Heart, and tryeth the Reins of Men.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third thing, whereby we have fomented Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions by a Deviation from the Divine Rule, <hi>Is a not walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together in things wherein we are agreed, becauſe of ſome things in which we are not agreed.</hi> That we may walk together in nothing, becauſe we are not agreed in all things, is one of the wildeſt and moſt dividing No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions a Chriſtian can entertain, directly contrary to the Apoſtolical Rule, <hi>Phil. 3. 16. Nevertheleſs, whereto we</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>have already attained, let us walk by the ſame Rule, let us mind the ſame thing.</hi> He walks with his Brother far enough, who walks with him as far as the ſhooes of the Goſpel will carry him; and he is very uncharitable, who becauſe his Brother is willing to walk this one Mile with him, will force him to walk two. I mean as far as every (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) Ordinance of Man would carry him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A fourth thing is an <hi>over-eagerneſs to propagate our own particular Opinions.</hi> There are very few Chriſtians but have their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, their particular Opinions
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42746:19"/> and Judgments in ſome things, not neceſſary to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved or done in order to Salvation, but every Chriſtian is not bound to propagate ſuch Notions, eſpecially if the Unity and Peace of a Church will be broken and endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger'd by it. This is plainly the Apoſtles Rule. <hi>Hoſt thou</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Faith?</hi> that is, haſt thou a Perſuaſion of the truth of a Notion, wherein the generality of the Church wherewith thou walkeſt differeth from thee? <hi>Have it to thy ſelf before God,</hi> Keep thy particular Notion to thy ſelf, and live up to it in the preſence of God, but do not for it diſturb the Peace and Unity of others. Every Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Truth is not of that moment, as to ballance the breach of a Churches Peace and Unity. It is a ſtrange eagerneſs we ſhall obſerve in ſome to propagate an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion wherein they differ from others, and what a ſtreſs they lay upon it, as if no Salvation were to be had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Faith, no Communion to be kept with any otherwiſe minded to them, this will perpetuate diviſion to the Worlds end.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Error of Men hath been cauſed by a deviation of men from that Rule which <hi>Solomon</hi> gives us, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. 5. <note place="margin">Prov. 3. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Lean not too much to thine own underſtanding. Humility</hi> will teach us to think that others may have the Spirit of God as well as we, and nothing but <hi>Pride</hi> can prompt us to think that we are the only Perſons that cannot be deceived. It is true every one muſt ſo far lean upon his own underſtanding, as to live and walk according to the dictate of his own Conſcience and ſpeak, and act, as he believeth, but he is not ſo far to lean upon it, as to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and condemn all thoſe that are not of his mind.</p>
            <p n="6">6. A ſixth Error, which hath broken our Unity, hath been our <hi>contending for truth,</hi> but <hi>not in love.</hi> This is <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 15.</note> alſo contrary to the Apoſtles. Precept <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Truthing in love,</hi> that is, maintaining the Truth, or practiſing what you judge Truth in Love. Some
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42746:19"/> Men indeed are ſo fond of their Notion, that they will not indure a word to be ſaid againſt them, this is an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fondneſs; but there are many that cannot bear a <hi>deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them,</hi> or <hi>reviling them</hi> for maintaining ſuch a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or being of ſuch a Party. <hi>If a man ſtrive</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>he is not Crowned, except he ſtrive lawfully.</hi> To gain a truth with the loſs of love, is a very ill Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, if the Notion of Truth be not ſuch as Salvation and Damnation depends upon an aſſent to, or a diſſent from it. Nor is there more need of quarrels in theſe ſtrivings, than there is of Mens Enmity one to another, becauſe they are enforced to try a title at Law one with another, whiles one Man thinks an Eſtate is his right, which the other judgeth his, which would make all going to Law a very ſinful thing. But there is no need of any ſuch En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, while both are or ſhould conſent to this, That they deſire the Eſtate may be his whoſe the Legal right is; whiles in this caſe all Chriſtians deſire that the <hi>Truth of God might prevail:</hi> What is their arguing and diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but a <hi>Tryal</hi> at the Bar of Scripture and Reaſon, what is Truth in the caſe? what needs any breach of Charity for this? If (which all will pretend to) Men did ſincerely deſire that what is <hi>truth</hi> might obtain; but the miſchief is bottomed in Mens <hi>inſincerity</hi> in thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, and unwillingneſs to be convinced.</p>
            <p n="7">7. A ſeventh deviation from the Divine Rule, which hath cauſed our breaches, Is a not bearing <hi>one anothers Infirmities,</hi> directly contrary to the Apoſtles determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>Rom. 15. 1. We then that are ſtrong ought to bear</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15. 1.</note> 
               <hi>the Infirmities of the weak, and not to pleaſe our ſelves.</hi> All Men have their infirmities, ſome <hi>in their underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> ſome <hi>in their Paſſions,</hi> every one cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend things that are true, with that clearneſs as others can, contrary to the judgment of their own Conſciences, in the things of God they cannot act; What then? muſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42746:20"/> we therefore hate them and malign them, and ſeek their ruin? is this a bearing with their Infirmities. Beſides, there are many Propoſitions of Truth, the Truth of which will not be evident till the Day of Judgment, and that day will determine in ſuch caſes who are <hi>the ſtrong</hi> and who <hi>the weak.</hi> But Men are ſo for <hi>pleaſing themſelves,</hi> that they can bear no Contradictions, no Diſputings of their Sentiments. Hence are the breaches of this Unity which produce ſo much unhappineſs to a People, as the maintaining of it would produce happineſs.</p>
            <p n="8">8. I ſhall add but one thing more; That is, A not marking thoſe who unneceſſarily <hi>make diviſions, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding them.</hi> This is alſo contrary to the Apoſtles rule, <hi>Rom. 16. 17.—Mark them which make diviſions amongſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16. 17.</note> 
               <hi>you, contrary to the Doctrine which you have learned, and avoid them.</hi> Thoſe make <hi>unneceſſary</hi> diviſions, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide where no Law of God obligeth them to divide, to ſecure the peace of their own Conſciences. A Man is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to follow the dictate of his own Conſcience, and to do what that tells him God's Word obligeth him to do, and to avoid what that tells him would be Sin unto him. All other Diviſions are unneceſſary. Now all theſe ought to be marked and avoided, as the common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Humane Society, a returning to thoſe Rules which God's Word hath left us, is the only way I know to bring us to that Happineſs, which the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren will bring us to. I will add but 4 things more, which ſhall be more extenſive, for the avoiding of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches upon civil accounts, and ſo conclude my Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe that would diſpoſe themſelves to live in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> one with another, muſt prepoſſeſs themſelves with this. That there is none but muſt have their allowances.—<hi>Nemo ſine crimine vivit.</hi> (ſaith the Poet <hi>Optimus ille qui minimis urgetur.</hi> He is not the beſt Man, who hath no Faults, but he that hath feweſt. He will hardly be able
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42746:20"/> to keep a Friend in the World, who hath not learn'd this, but reſolves to quarrel with him upon every offence. Hence it is that the <hi>forbearance</hi> of one another is in Scripture preſſed ſo often upon Chriſtians as their duty, <hi>Eph. 4. 2. Coloſ.</hi> 3. 13. where <hi>forgiving</hi> one another is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo added. He that cannot both <hi>forbear</hi> and <hi>forgive,</hi> will not long keep in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> with any.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Study Humility,</hi> and a mean opinion of your ſelves. The humble Man is commonly reconciled to the world. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, That <hi>only by pride cometh contention.</hi> He that muſt exalt himſelf, and his own Sentiments, above all other Mens, will hardly find any but Flatterers long agreeing with him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Avoid <hi>Self ſeeking.</hi> It is an admirable direction of the Apoſtle, <hi>Let no man ſeek his own, but anothers wealth, 1 Cor.</hi> 10. 24. He that only ſeeketh himſelf, loveth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alone, and muſt be contented to be loved by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alone.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Above all, <hi>Hatred, Malice, Envy,</hi> and all peeviſh Paſſions muſt be mortified. The Apoſtle ſpeaks of theſe as things which he ſuppoſeth all good Chriſtians to have <hi>put off</hi> and <hi>mortified.</hi> Indeed they are all <hi>works of the Fleſh,</hi> directly oppoſite to this work and <hi>fruit of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> I ſhall now conclude, Begging of God to bring us to ſuch a temper, that we may arrive at ſuch an Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:42746:21"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Catalogue of Books Printed for, and are to be Sold by</hi> Edw. Giles, <hi>Bookseller in</hi> Norwich, <hi>near the</hi> Market-Place.</head>
            <p>SEveral Diſcourſes concerning Actual Providence.</p>
            <p>A Word in Seaſon.</p>
            <p>Defenſwe Armour againſt four of <hi>Satan</hi>'s moſt fiery Darts.</p>
            <p>Sermons upon the whole firſt and ſecond Chapter of the <hi>Canticles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirteen Sermons upon ſeveral uſeful Subjects; all Publiſhed by <hi>John Collins,</hi> D. D. of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The way of the Spirit in bringing Souls to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Glory of Chriſt ſet forth, with the neceſſity of Faith, in ſeveral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: both by Mr. <hi>Thomas Allen,</hi> late Paſtor of a Church at <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Enoch</hi>'s Walk with God and Chriſt, a Chriſtian's Gain: by Mr. <hi>Timothy Armitage,</hi> late Miniſter at <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of the preciouſneſs of Chriſt, and of the preciouſneſs of Faith.</p>
            <p>Precious Promiſes the Portion of Overcomers.</p>
            <p>Sermons on five ſeveral uſeful Subjects; all by Mr. <hi>John L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gher,</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Saints <hi>Ehenezer,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Francis Engliſh,</hi> late Miniſter in <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Directions to ſpell <hi>Engliſh</hi> right.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the <hi>Proteſtant Reformation,</hi> as it was begun by <hi>Luther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Dead Saint ſpeaking; being a Sermon preached upon the Death of Mr. <hi>Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>comb</hi> of <hi>Dedham</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſh Presbyterian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Miracles of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The ordinary matter of Prayer, drawn into Queſtions and Anſwers.</p>
            <p>Two Treatiſes, the firſt, Rejoycing in the Lord Jeſus in all Caſes and Conditions: The ſecond, Of a Chriſtian's Hope in Heaven, and Freedom from Condemnation by Chriſt: both by Mr. <hi>Robert Aſty,</hi> late Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt in <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obedience to Magiſtrates, recommended in a Sermon preached <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> the 9th, 1683. being the Thankſgiving Day for His Majeſties Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: by <hi>Jonathan Clapham,</hi> Rector of <hi>Wramplingham</hi> in <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Preſent for Youth, and an Example for the Aged; Two Diſcourſes, one of Spiritual Bleſſings; the other, That God hath an high account of the leaſt Grace in the Saints: by Mr. <hi>John Cromwell,</hi> late Paſtor of a Church of Chriſt in <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Infant Baptiſm of Chriſt's Appointment: by Mr. <hi>Samuel Petto,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Sudbury</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the Converſion of Sinners to God in Chriſt, the neceſſity, nature, means, and ſigns of it, with a concluding Speech to the Unconverted: by <hi>Martin Finch,</hi> a Servant of Chriſt in the Work of the Goſpel, in the City of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sincerity, or the upright Man's Walk to Heaven, delivered, in ſeveral Sermons in the Pariſh Church of St. <hi>Michael,</hi> in <hi>Long-ſtratton,</hi> in <hi>Norfolk:</hi> by <hi>James-Oldfield,</hi> late Miniſter there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexipharmacon Spirituale.</hi> Being a Defenſative againſt the <hi>Poiſon and Sting of Death.</hi> Or, The great Expedient how to make the Bed of the Grave ſo eaſie, that we may lye down in Peace, and take our Reſt. By <hi>S. Snowden.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
